Ten years ago,
منذ عشر سنوات،
I had my first exhibition here.
كان معرضي الأول هنا.
I had no idea if it would work or was at all possible,
لم تكن لي أدنى فكرة إن كان هذا الأمر سينجح أو إن كان ممكنًا حتى،
but with a few small steps and a very steep learning curve,
لكن من خلال خطوات بسيطة ومنحنى تعليمي
I made my first sculpture, called "The Lost Correspondent."
صنعت أول منحوتاتي وأسميتها "المراسل المفقود."
Teaming up with a marine biologist and a local dive center,
شكلت فريقًا مع بيولوجي بحري ومركز محلي للغطس،
I submerged the work off the coast of Grenada,
أغرقت العمل في ساحل غرناطة،
in an area decimated by Hurricane Ivan.
في منطقة دمرها إعصار إيفان.
And then this incredible thing happened.
فحصل هذا الأمر المذهل.
It transformed.
حصل التحول.
One sculpture became two.
منحوتة أصبحت اثنتين.
Two quickly became 26.
واثنتان صارت بسرعة 26.
And before I knew it,
وقبل أن أعي الأمر،
we had the world's first underwater sculpture park.
كان لدينا أول حديقة منحوتات تحت الماء.
In 2009, I moved to Mexico and started by casting local fisherman.
سنة 2009، انتقلت إلى المكسيك وبدأت في اختيار صيادين محليين.
This grew to a small community,
فكبر الأمر حتى أصبح تجمعًا صغيرًا،
to almost an entire movement of people in defense of the sea.
إلى أن صار حركة كاملة من الناس الذين يدافعون عن البحر.
And then finally, to an underwater museum,
ثم في النهاية إلى، معرض تحت الماء،
with over 500 living sculptures.
بوجود 500 منحوتة حية.
Gardening, it seems, is not just for greenhouses.
الاهتمام بالحدائق، على مايبدو، ليس من اختصاص الدفيئات فحسب.
We've since scaled up the designs:
منذ ذلك الحين، قمنا بالارتقاء بالتصاميم:
"Ocean Atlas," in the Bahamas, rising 16 feet up to the surface
"أوشن أطلس" في الباهاماس، حيث بلغ طولها 16 قدمًا حتى السطح
and weighing over 40 tons,
ووزنها فوق الأربعين طنًا،
to now currently in Lanzarote,
إلى حيث هي الآن في لانزاروتي،
where I'm making an underwater botanical garden,
حيث أقوم الآن بإنشاء حديقة خضراء تحت الماء،
the first of its kind in the Atlantic Ocean.
الأولى من نوعها في المحيط الأطلسي.
Each project, we use materials and designs that help encourage life;
في كل مشروع، نستعمل موادًا و تصاميم تساعد على تشجيع الحياة؛
a long-lasting pH-neutral cement provides a stable and permanent platform.
يوفر الإسمنت ذو الحمض المحايد طويل المدى منصة مستقرة ودائمة.
It is textured to allow coral polyps to attach.
صمم نسيجه ليسمح لسرطان البحر أن يتشبث.
We position them down current from natural reefs
ونضعه في الأسفل حول الشعب المرجانية الطبيعية
so that after spawning, there's areas for them to settle.
بشكل يجعلها تجد مناطق لتستقر بها بعد أن تضع بيضها.
The formations are all configured so that they aggregate fish
يتم تكوين جميع التشكيلات بحيث يمكن للسمك أن يتجمع
on a really large scale.
بشكل أوسع بكثير.
Even this VW Beetle has an internal living habitat
حتى "في دبليو بييتل" هذه بها مسكن داخلي
to encourage crustaceans such as lobsters and sea urchins.
لتشجيع القشريات مثل الكركند و قنافذ البحر.
So why exhibit my work in the ocean?
إذن لماذا أعرض عملي في المحيط؟
Because honestly, it's really not easy.
صدقًا لأنه عمل غير يسير.
When you're in the middle of the sea under a hundred-foot crane,
عندما تكون في عرض البحر تحت رافعة ذات مئة قدم،
trying to lower eight tons down to the sea floor,
محاولًا إنزال 8 أطنان إلى قاع البحر،
you start to wonder whether I shouldn't have taken up watercolor painting instead.
تبدأ في التساؤل إن كان علي أن أرسم بالماء عوضًا عن كل هذا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But in the end, the results always blow my mind.
لكن في النهاية، دائمًا ما تبهرني النتيجة.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
The ocean is the most incredible exhibition space
المحيط هو فضاء العرض الأكثر إدهاشًا
an artist could ever wish for.
الذي قد يتمناه أي فنان.
You have amazing lighting effects changing by the hour,
لديك مؤثرات ضوئية تتغير كل ساعة،
explosions of sand covering the sculptures in a cloud of mystery,
انفجارات في الرمل تغطي المنحوتات بسحب من السحر،
a unique timeless quality
جودة لا يمحوها الزمان
and the procession of inquisitive visitors,
ومواكب من الزوار الفضوليين،
each lending their own special touch to the site.
حيث يضع كل منهم لمسة مميزة على الموقع.
(Music)
(موسيقى)
But over the years,
لكن بمرور السنوات،
I've realized that the greatest thing about what we do,
أدركت أن أعظم ما نقوم به في هذا الشأن،
the really humbling thing about the work,
الأمر الذي يجعلنا أكثر تواضعًا،
is that as soon as we submerge the sculptures,
هو بمجرد ما نغرق المنحوتات،
they're not ours anymore,
فهي تخرج من ملكيتنا،
because as soon as we sink them,
لأننا لحظة إغراقها،
the sculptures, they belong to the sea.
فهي تصبح ملكًا للبحر.
As new reefs form, a new world literally starts to evolve,
مع تشكل شعب بحرية جديدة، يبدأ عالم جديد في التطور، حرفيًا.
a world that continuously amazes me.
وهو عالم يبهرني باستمرار.
It's a bit of a cliché, but nothing man-made
قد يبدو الموضوع مستهلكًا، لكن لا يمكن لشيء صنعه الإنسان
can ever match the imagination of nature.
أن يصل إلى خيال الطبيعة.
Sponges look like veins across the faces.
يبدو الإسفنج البحري كالعروق على الأوجه.
Staghorn coral morphs the form.
يشكل المرجان الشكل النهائي.
Fireworms scrawl white lines as they feed.
يرسم خطوطًا بيضاء بينما يتغذى.
Tunicates explode from the faces.
تنفجرالغلاليات من الوجوه.
Sea urchins crawl across the bodies feeding at night.
تزحف قنافذ البحر ليلًا داخل الأجسام لتتغذى.
Coralline algae applies a kind of purple paint.
تضع الطحالب المرجانية نوعًا من الطلاء البنفسجي.
The deepest red I've ever seen in my life lives underwater.
اللون الأحمر القاني الأكثر عمقًا الذي رأيته في حياتي يوجد تحت الماء.
Gorgonian fans oscillate with the waves.
يتذبذب المرجان المروحي مع الأمواج.
Purple sponges breathe water like air.
يتنفس الإسفنج البنفسجي الماء كما لو كان هواء.
And grey angelfish glide silently overhead.
وتنزلق السمكة الملائكية بهدوء في المكان.
And the amazing response we've had to these works
والتجاوب الرائع الذي حصلنا عليه مع هذه الأعمال
tells me that we've managed to plug into something really primal,
يخبرني أننا نجحنا في الارتباط مع شيء نعتبره بدائيًا فعلًا،
because it seems that these images translate across the world,
لأنه يبدو أن هذه الصور تترجم على مدى العالم،
and that's made me focus on my responsibility as an artist
وهذا ما جعلني أركز على مسؤوليتي كفنان
and about what I'm trying to achieve.
وعلى ما أحاول أن أصل إليه.
I'm standing here today on this boat in the middle of the ocean,
أقف هنا اليوم على هذا القارب في عرض المحيط،
and this couldn't be a better place
وما من مكان أفضل من هذا
to talk about the really, really important effect of my work.
للحديث عن تأثير عملي بالغ الأهمية.
Because as we all know,
لأنه كما نعلم جميعًا،
our reefs are dying, and our oceans are in trouble.
فإن الشعب المرجانية تموت ومحيطاتنا تعاني الكثير.
So here's the thing:
لذا إليكم ما يلي:
the most used, searched and shared image
أكثر صورة تم استعمالها و البحث عنها و مشاركتها
of all my work thus far is this.
من مجموع كل أعمالي حتى الآن هي هذه الصورة.
And I think this is for a reason,
وأعتقد أن ذلك راجع لسبب ما،
or at least I hope it is.
أو على الأقل، آمل ذلك.
What I really hope is that people are beginning to understand
ما أتمناه حقًا أن يبدأ الناس في فهم
that when we think of the environment and the destruction of nature,
أنه حين نبدأ التفكير في البيئة وإيذاء الطبيعة،
that we need to start thinking about our oceans, too.
بأنه علينا أن نبدأ في التفكير في المحيطات أيضًا،
Since building these sites, we've seen some phenomenal
منذ بناء هذه المواقع، رأينا بعضًا من النتائج
and unexpected results.
المدهشة وغير المتوقعة.
Besides creating over 800 square meters of new habitats and living reef,
إلى جانب خلق 800 متر مربع من المساكن الجديدة للشعب المرجانية الحية،
visitors to the marine park in Cancun now divide half their time
يقسم زوار الحديقة البحرية في كانكون نصف وقتهم
between the museum and the natural reefs,
بين المتحف والشعب المرجانية الطبيعية،
providing significant rest for natural, overstressed areas.
مانحين بذلك بعضًا من الراحة للمناطق الطبيعية الأكثر زيارة.
Visitors to "Ocean Atlas" in the Bahamas highlighted a leak
ألقى زوار"أوشن أطلس" في الباهاماس الضوء على تسرب
from a nearby oil refinery.
من مصفاة بترولية قريبة.
The subsequent international media forced the local government
التغطية الإعلامية العالمية التي تلت الحدث أجبرت الحكومة المحلية
to pledge 10 million dollars in coastal cleanups.
على التعهد بصرف 10 ملايين دولار لتنظيف السواحل.
The sculpture park in Grenada was instrumental
حديقة المنحوتات بغرناطة كانت ذات نفع كبير
in the government designating a spot -- a marine-protected area.
بالنسبة للحكومة في تصنيف المكان-- كمنطقة بحرية محمية.
Entrance fees to the park now help fund park rangers
تساهم رسوم دخول الحديقة في تمويل حراس الحديقة
to manage tourism and fishing quotas.
لإدارة السياحة وحصص الصيد.
The site was actually listed as a "Wonder of the World"
تم تصنيف الموقع كواحد من "عجائب العالم"
by National Geographic.
من طرف ناشيونال جيوغرافيك.
So why are we all here today in this room?
إذن لم نحن كلنا اليوم مجتمعون في هذه القاعة؟
What do we all have in common?
ما القاسم المشترك بيننا؟
I think we all share a fear
أعنقد أننا جميعًا نتقاسم الخوف
that we don't protect our oceans enough.
من أننا لا نقوم بحماية المحيطات بما يكفي.
And one way of thinking about this
وإحدى طرق التفكير في هذا
is that we don't regard our oceans as sacred,
هو أننا لا نعتبر محيطاتنا كشيء مقدس،
and we should.
كما ينبغي علينا.
When we see incredible places --
حينما نرى أماكن مذهلة--
like the Himalayas or the La Sagrada Família,
كالهيمالايا أو لا ساغادا فاميليا،
or the Mona Lisa, even --
أو حتى الموناليزا--
when we see these incredible places and things,
حينما نرى هذه الأماكن أو الأشياء المذهلة،
we understand their importance.
نعي أهميتها.
We call them sacred,
ونصفها بالمقدسة.
and we do our best to cherish them, to protect them
ونقوم بما في وسعنا للاحتفاء بها، والحفاظ عليها
and to keep them safe.
وإبقائها محمية.
But in order to do that,
ولكن للقيام بهذا،
we are the ones that have to assign that value;
فنحن من يجب علينا إعطاء هذه القيمة،
otherwise, it will be desecrated
وإلا، سيتم تدنيسها
by someone who doesn't understand that value.
على يد من لا يفهمون قيمتها.
So I want to finish up tonight by talking about sacred things.
لذلك فإنني أريد أن أختم الليلة بالحديث عن الأشياء المقدسة.
When we were naming the site in Cancun,
حينما كنا نختار اسمًا للموقع في كانكون،
we named it a museum for a very important and simple reason:
سميناه متحفًا لسبب بسيط ومهم جدًا:
museums are places of preservation,
أن المتاحف هي أماكن للمحافظة
of conservation and of education.
والحفاظ والتعلم.
They're places where we keep objects of great value to us,
هي أماكن حين يمكننا أن نحتفظ بأشياء ذات قيمة بالنسبة لنا،
where we simply treasure them for them being themselves.
حيث نحتفي بها بكونها ما هي عليه فقط.
If someone was to throw an egg at the Sistine Chapel,
إذا رمى شخص بيضة على سيستسن شابيل،
we'd all go crazy.
فسنصاب بالجنون جميعنا.
If someone wanted to build a seven-star hotel
إذا أراد أحد بناء فندق ذي سبع نجوم
at the bottom of the Grand Canyon,
في سفح الأخدود العظيم،
then we would laugh them out of Arizona.
فسنرميه خارج أريزونا.
Yet every day we dredge, pollute and overfish our oceans.
لكننا بالمقابل في كل يوم نلتقط المحار، نلوث و نصطاد بشكل جائر من محيطاتنا.
And I think it's easier for us to do that,
وأعتقد أنه من السهل علينا القيام بهذا،
because when we see the ocean,
لأننا حين نرى المحيط،
we don't see the havoc we're wreaking.
لا نرى الخراب الذي نتسبب فيه.
Because for most people,
لأنه بالنسبة لمعظم الناس،
the ocean is like this.
فالمحيط يبدو هكذا.
And it's really hard
وإنه لمن الصعب
to think of something that's just so plain and so enormous, as fragile.
التفكير في أن شيئًا عاديًا وضخمًا، قد يكون هشًا.
It's simply too massive, too vast, too endless.
فهو ببساطة، كبير جدًا وواسع جدًا، ولا متناه جدًا.
And what do you see here?
فما الذي ترونه هنا؟
I think most people actually look past to the horizon.
أعتقد أن معظم الناس ستجاوزون الرؤية ليروا الأفق.
So I think there's a real danger
لذا أعتقد أن هناك خطرًا كبيرًا
that we never really see the sea,
أننا لا نرى البحر مطلقًا،
and if we don't really see it,
وإن لم نكن نره حقًا،
if it doesn't have its own iconography,
إن لم تكن له أيقونيته الخاصة به،
if we miss its majesty,
إذا أغفلنا جلالته،
then there's a big danger that we take it for granted.
فعندها سيكون هناك خطر كبير في أننا نعتبره شيئًا من المسلّمات.
Cancun is famous for spring break,
كانكون معروفة بكونها مكان للعطلة الربيعية،
tequila and foam parties.
وحفلات التيكيلا والرغوة.
And its waters are where frat boys can ride around on Jet Skis
ومياهها حيث يقود الفتية دراجاتهم المائية
and banana boats.
وقوارب الموز.
But because of our work there, there's now a little corner of Cancun
ولكن و بسبب عملنا هناك، هناك الآن ركن صغير من كانكون
that is simply precious for being itself.
ذو قيمة كبيرة ببساطة لأنه هناك.
And we don't want to stop in Grenada,
ونحن لا نريد التوقف عند غرناطة،
in Cancun or the Bahamas.
كانكون أو الباهاماس.
Just last month, I installed these Four Horsemen of the Apocalypse
فقط خلال الشهر الماضي، وضعت "أربعة فرسان من نهاية الزمان"
in the Thames River,
في نهر تاميس،
in central London, right in front of the Houses of Parliament,
في قلب لندن، أمام مقر البرلمان تمامًا،
putting a stark message about climate change
واضعين بذلك رسالة صارخة حول تغير المناخ
in front of the people that have the power to help change things.
أمام من لهم السلطة في المساعدة على تغيير الأشياء.
Because for me, this is just the beginning of the mission.
لأنه بالنسبة لي، فهذه هي بداية المهمة.
We want to team up with other inventors,
نريد أن نشكل فرقًا مع مخترعين آخرين،
creators, philanthropists, educators, biologists,
مبدعين، فاعلي خير، مربين وعلماء أحياء،
to see better futures for our oceans.
لرؤية مستقبل أفضل لمحيطاتنا.
And we want to see beyond sculpture,
نريد أن نرى ما وراء المنحوتات،
beyond art, even.
ما وراء الفن حتى.
Say you're a 14-year-old kid from the city,
فلتقل أن عمرك 14 سنة وتعيش في المدينة،
and you've never seen the ocean.
ولم تر المحيط في حياتك قط.
And instead of getting taken to the natural history museum
وعوضًا من أن يأخذوك في نزهة إلى متحف التاريخ الوطني
or an aquarium,
أو معرض للأحياء المائية،
you get taken out to the ocean,
سيأخذونك إلى المحيط،
to an underwater Noah's Ark,
إلى قوس نوح تحت المائي،
which you can access through a dry-glass viewing tunnel,
الذي يمكنك الدخول إليه عبر نفق رؤية جاف،
where you can see all the wildlife of the land
حيث يمكنك رؤية الحياة البرية في الأرض
be colonized by the wildlife of the ocean.
تحتلُّها الحياة البرية للمحيط.
Clearly, it would blow your mind.
بكل تأكيد فهذا سيذهلك.
So let's think big and let's think deep.
لذا فلنفكر بشكل أكبر وأعمق.
Who knows where our imagination and willpower can lead us?
من يدري إلى أين سيأخذنا خيالنا وقوة عزيمتنا؟
I hope that by bringing our art into the ocean,
آمل أنه من خلال جلب الفن إلى المحيط،
that not only do we take advantage of amazing creativity
لن نستغل الإبداع الخلاق
and visual impact of the setting,
والتأثير البصري للموقع.
but that we are also giving something back,
بل أن نمنح شيئًا بالمقابل،
and by encouraging new environments to thrive,
ومن خلال تشجيع بيئات جديدة لتزدهر،
and in some way opening up a new -- or maybe it's a really old way
وبطريقة أو بأخرى أن نفتح طريقًا جديدة-- أو ربما هي قديمة فعلًا
of seeing the seas:
لرؤية البحار:
as delicate, precious places,
على أنها أماكن غالية وحساسة،
worthy of our protection.
تستحق حمايتنا لها.
Our oceans are sacred.
محيطاتنا مقدسة.
Thank you.
شكرًا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)